Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Burma Videotapes, circa 1990-2002 RL.00605
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Burma Videotapes, circa 1990-2002, 287 videocassettes
  - BBC: Sacrifice, NTSC VHS [TRT 01:00:00] (Box 286, Video-cassette BU034)
    Some girls go and some came home. Some looked different. Some of them showed some extent of prosperity and some were sick. One was told to help her aunt by going to Thailand. The other was not allowed by parents. One was a widow with a baby. She crossed border to find a job to support the ailing mother and her boy. Stories of those three girls and their patrons, and the pain that they suffer. Reaction and lack of response from the Burmese and Thai governments. Girls endured 10 to 12 men a day, over 300 men a year. One got pregnant but pimp wanted her to keep the baby so that the baby would be raised to become a prostitute. Police caught them demanding money for the release. They imprisoned them. A drunken police raped them. They ran away.
    Included are vivid pictures of child prostitution.
  - NDI: Suu Kyi's Message to NDI - Burma's situation 1996., NTSC VHS [TRT 00:10:00] (3 copies) (Box 286, Video-cassette BU035)
    Produced by: National Democratic Institute
    National Democratic Institute for International Affairs, narrated by Aung San Suu Kyi.
    Acknowledgement from Aung San Suu Kyi on receipt of the W. Evert Hurriman Award.
    Scenes from Burma, narrated by Aung San Suu Kyi: Democracy is people's will, not the will of leaders who want to rule with absolute power. Democracy is people's involvement in politics. That was how the 1988 people's upraising took place in Burma.People were fed up. They needed only a spark to start the full blown revolution. That uprising was cracked down. She knew the right time had come. National League for Democracy (NLD) was formed for the election. Aung San Suu Kyi's name was magic. State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) started to disrupt her and finally kept her under house arrest. In spite of all kind of oppression, NLD won the election. SLORC ignored the results and jailed the MPs. When released in 1995 she began the gate speeches. Fear was the most destructive factor in Burma.
    Suu Kyi said she was honored to receive this award on behalf of everyone who struggled for democracy in Burma and the people of Burma. Human rights abuses did not decline. They worsened instead. NLD had been harassed. Many working committees were forced to close. With help of the people who love peace and justice and the relentless will of the people to be free we will achieve our goal.
  - Channel 4: Burma - Dying for Democracy, NTSC VHS [TRT 01:30:00] (Box 286, Video-cassette BU036)
    Produced by: Channel 4 Great Britain, Christopher Mould
    Students chanted the song "Burma, our land. This is our time to go out and fight for freedom."
    LSD upsets the military leadership. The Demonetization triggered massive bankruptcy. People held a demonstration. Army responded, killing 42 people.
    State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) took power. They killed hundreds of people. Army said they were looters. Min Win: "The army shot us from the roofs in front of US embassy. "Thet Naing Aung: "I saw a girl shot at her leg. One nurse rushed to the girl but bullets hit both of them. I saw them both went dead."
    Zaw Oo: "We protested peacefully but they shot us unarmed civilians. They arrested many and female inmates were raped."
    Soe Min: "We were asked to disperse but we refused. Then they shot at us. Many died. Some of them were just passers-by."
    Ye Gaung, a Journalist: "We want democracy. We will never get it in the presence of military government."
    Tanimsarim river bank, the Karen National Union (KNU) camp. Saw Lone: "On one side is brutality of the regime, on the other is the rumors of arriving foreign aid. It is a new chapter in Burmese history."
    Myint Thein All Burma Students' Democratic Front (ABSDF): "We will fight hand in hand with ethics."
    Than Minn Htun: "My daughter was weak; she fell when bullet hit her. But my son who was brushed by bullets did not die. They stabbed him threw him and my daughter to the fire."
    Teak and black market sources of Karen National Union (KNU) income. Manaplaw hospital. Bo Mya giving awardto the disabled. The National Democratic Front.
    "I don't want to see more lives lost," said Cho Cho Kyaw Nyein.
    Preparation for election; Thakin Chit Maung; heavy inflation.
    Khin Nyunt: "We don't restrict any parties as long as they operate under law."
    The National League for Democracy (NLD)'s U Tin Oo welcomed the election. Aung San Suu Kyi: "Army is not sincere. We fight for freedom with our way."
    "Burmese are never our enemies." Bo Mya.
    Breng Sang: "Peace is on the table not on the battle field."
    Saw Lone: "People expect the students to lead a change but they must move right."
  - Images Asia: Aung San Suu Kyi message to 55th United Nations Convention on Human Right, Geneva 1999, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:30:00] (Box 286, Video-cassette BU037)
    Produced by: Altsean andImages Asia
    Network: Images Asia
    Message: In 1998, State Peace and Development Council (SPCD) (formerly State Law and Order Restoration Council [SLORC]) stepped up the already worsened human rights abuses, making mass arrests of National League for Democracy (NLD) MPs and members. It was the Junta's response on NLD's attempt to convene the people's assembly with elected MPs. The NLD suffered eight months of last year over the past nine years of party's existence.
    Authorities acted like criminals in persecuting NLD. A lawsuit was filed against Ministry of Home and Military Intelligence but was not acted upon.We need concrete action, not just lip services.
    Comments on crack down: 150 MPs and 300 more members are in detention. Many were held without any charges.Many people don't know there are basic rights; people live in fear; no rule of law prevails. Since 1962 people have been living in constant fear of being persecuted.
    Comments on right of children: Burma signed the convention but did not respect it. Extremely malnourished children were often seen in the center of Rangoon. Many can't afford elementary education.
    Comments on child labor: Not much now in business sector because construction boom has died out. But many were seen in government projects.
    Comments on law for children and women: there is no such rule of law.
    Comments on present condition: Women and children are prime victims of instability in a country.Many turn to prostitution in hopes of a better life but many are facing starvation.
  - Amateur Footage: Burma at the Cross Roads, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:10:00] (2 copies) (Box 286 and 288, Video-cassette BU038)
    Produced by: Friedrich Ebert, Images Asia
    Address to International Forum on Burma; short comments on current issues of Burma 1999.
    The Speech:(In yellow Yinpone) Since the release of Aung San Suu Kyi nothing has so far changed toward democratization. The regime is doing everything to block the ways of democratization in Burma in the name of justice, peace and progress. Aung San Suu Kyi appealed to the international community to work for the implementation of United Nations Resolution on early return of democracy in Burma.
    Current economic situation in Burma: Price of petrol tripled, immediately causing abrupt price rise that hit the population. Inflation was painfully high. A few wealthy people got richer but the vast majority suffered.
    Investment. It did not benefit the ordinary people. Farming sector is worse off. Farmers are forced to sell their products to army with fixed price. People starved.
    Labor: No labor union to protect the laborers' rights.
    Current Political Situation: No one is absolutely safe under this regime. Government arrests anyone as they please. Government has no respect for its fellow citizens.
  - Amateur Footage: Unedited video footage of 1988 People's demonstration scenes in Rangoon, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:18:00] (2 copies) (Box 286 and 288, Video-cassette BU039)
    Produced by: Ed Thomas, Private Individual
    Demonstrators shouting slogans, holding banners on the top of buses and cars demanding democracy in Burma. Few soldiers were seen. People from various sectors joined the demonstration.
  - Border Line Production: Fear in the Forest, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:20:00] (2 copies) (Box 286 and 288, Video-cassette BU040)
    Produced by: Border Line Production
    Edited report on the living condition of Karen Minorities under Burmese army advances, 1998.
    "I can hide in front of others but my heart is full of sorrow."
    In the name of border area development and in an attempt to boost the trade ties with neighboring Thailand, Junta crushed the rebellion of Karen minorities and civilians. Naw Htoo, 26 years old, fled Burma when her family was forcibly relocated to Myitta village. They left their own village, leaving everything behind. They were settled but given no food allowance. Soldiers took them as porters. Her domestic animals were taken by soldiers when starvation struck them. Her husband's brother and father ventured back to the village they abandoned to harvest rice in order to feed them. Soldiers caught them and shot them after torturing them. Naw Htoo fled to Thailand and worked hard, but Thai soldiers often harassed her. Naw Tha's family escaped to Thailand but her husband died of tuberculosis. Her husband was never treated before.
    Many took refuge in the jungle and were not allowed to leave. Living conditions deteriorated.Children died of malaria, dysentery and many diseases that were easily treatable in clinics.
  - ABC: Nightline - Land Mine Survivors' Stories, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:15:00] (2 copies) (Box 286, Video-cassette BU041)
    Produced by: Borderline Video Production
    Airing Program: Nightline
    Land mine victims - civil war in Burma.
    Feelings of agony, pain, loss and tremendous courage and determination of some amputees.
    It was the world's longest civil war: the war betweenthe Burmese Junta and Karen National Union claimed countless lives. Both sides placed thousands of land mines in the war zone that continue to claim victims of all ages.
    A porter stepped on a mine. Soldiers abandoned him, gave him no help. Karen National Union (KNU) soldiers rescued him. Another farmer stepped on a mine while collecting some vegetables.
    A female farmer was hit on a rocky trail while picking honey for the nurses. Victims feel terrible heartbreak. They would prefer to die. Some actually ask soldiers to shoot them. Stories of individuals who faced enormous losses and discrimination but who have recovered and are leading normal lives.
    A prosthesis clinic in a refugee camp serviced a total of 50,000 since it was founded.
    New Year sports festival of those who were disabled by land mines. It was fun and hopeful. "I am not disappointed. I have difficulties. I need a companion. But if anyone helps me or not, I can live like this."
  - Images Asia: Facing the Fire (1977), NTSC VHS [TRT 00:20:00] (2 copies) (Box 286, Video-cassette BU042)
    Produced by: Images Asia-Lyndall Barry
    "Airing Program: Road to Nowhere: An Investigation into Forced Labor in Burma"
    Edited report by Borderline Video: Renewed Refugee Chaos in Thai and Burma Border. Local Karens left home to escape atrocities committed by Burmese soldiers to go to Thailand.
    After Karen National Union (KNU) split with the Democratic Karen Buddhist Army (DKBA) in 1995,their headquarters fell. In the next two years, army advanced, forced tens of thousands of villagers to flee Burma. Army forcibly relocated the villagers, clearing the whole area.Those relocated villages became labor pool for army. Those who escaped to Thailand were put in the camps near border. In the January 1997 New Year celebration at Mae La camp, the DKBA, with the help of Burma army, executed a series of cross border raids, and burned and killed the refugees. Thai Army refused to do anything.The KNU 4th Brigade commander, "Oliver,"was interviewed. KNU with All Burma Students' Democratic Front (ABSDF) abandoned the fixed camp warfare and adopted guerrilla warfare. Thai army turned away male refugees. Many were still trapped in the Burma side of jungle. Soldiers were ordered to kill anyone who tried to flee or returned to the village to collect food they left behind. Refugees had to live on roadsides and everywhere. Rumors of not being accepted by Thai authority scared away hundreds. They went back to the malaria-infested jungles. There was no medicine and not enough food.
    Medica San Frontier continued to provide supplies but was not allowed to visit the newly opened camps.
  - VOA: Audio Interviews, NTSC VHS [TRT 01:00:00] (Box 287, Video-cassette BU043)
    Produced by: Voice of America, 1997
    Voices of Tun Naing Oo, Tun Lin, Cynthia Maung, Kevin Hepner, Wahdoo Htoo.
  - Images Asia: Road to Nowhere, NTSC Betacam SP [TRT 00:40:00] (2 copies) (Box 287, Video-cassette BU044)
    Produced by: Images Asia for ILO
    This documentary is based on the findings of a 1998 report published by the International Labor Organization (ILO) inquiry on forced labor issues in Burma. The ILO found Burma guilty of "widespread and systematic forced labor," turning the country into "a virtual slave labor camp." The regime refused to attend ILO hearings, denying any use of forced labor.
    Laborers include men, women, elderly and children. They are forced to purchase the materials that they are forced to work on.
    Footage: road construction, laborers loading baskets with rocks, construction sites, workers in rural rice fields, poverty, villagers working on farms, soldiers marching through streets, paper orders from the army demanding quotas for forced labor, convict labor, construction of foreign investments and tourist sites, gas pipeline construction for Total and Unocal, emptied villages used for production sites.
    Interviews include: Bill Jordan, International Confederation of Trade Unions; Justice Bhagwati, ILO Commissioner; Lt. Col. Hal Min, Burmese Military Spokesman; Pierre Sane, Secretary General of Amnesty International; testimonies smuggled out of Burma, Aung San Suu Kyi, National League for Democracy (NLD) Leader; Robyn Layton, ILO Commissioner.
    Lt. Col. Hal Min (Military Representative): "Myanmar is a very strong Buddhist nation...our traditions, our culture does not allow for these things to happen. We get very frustrated when all these accusations are thrown at us when they say this is Myanmar at this present moment, this is something that really frustrates the government, not only the government, also the people of Myanmar"; Daw Aung San Suu Kyi: "Practically all roads built by the government use forced labor, roads, bridges, clearing out the jungle. All this needs forced labor because there is no other way the government can get this done.And we do not have the kind of machinery that will enable us to get these kind of projects going quickly. So it's human power that they need, man power, forced labor power"; International Labor Organization (ILO) Report: "Workers were not paid or compensated in any way for providing their labor, other than in exceptional circumstances...and were commonly subjected to various forms of verbal and physical abuse, including rape, torture, and killing"; Unidentified woman(working on road): "The biggest fine is 500 Kyat. If we don't dig a ditch or canal, we pay 500 Kyat. What can we do? We're poor. It's a daily struggle to get food. Now we're here, we have to do this forced labor. I wonder what's happening at home."
    According to this documentary, locals were angry when they were ordered to demolish the ancient pagodas and monasteries to build new ones. The ancient artifacts were taken away. Voice-over: DANA is Burmese word for contributing to Buddha. When the government forces people to do Dana, it is like they have exhorted the position of Buddha.
    Documentary also reports on foreign companies contributing to the use of forced labor. Total and Unocal built Yadana pipeline with forced labor, although the companies deny this.
  - ABC: Nightline - Free From Fear, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:25:00] (Box 287, Video-cassette BU045)
    Produced by: ABC Nightline
    Report on the release of Nobel Peace Prize National League for Democracy (NLD) leader Aung San Suu Kyi's from six years of house arrest. She gives her first interview to Fargal King of BBC.
    Aung San Suu Kyi said she read a lot and listened to the radio, but chose not to write because she did not want State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) to see her writings. She thanks the people around the world for their support and stresses the importance ofthe opinion of the international community.
    Aung San Suu Kyi: "The idea of real freedom which I have always said is freedom from fear .I was free because I was not frightened. So for me real freedom is freedom from fear."
    The program also includes a report from Hillary Brown on the Burmese government's tourist campaign to attract half a million people. She shot footage of forced labor gangs made up mainly of women and children, an interview with Buddhist monk who states that the people of Burma are afraid of to talk, and reports on a village that was demolished because the government believed that they were too "friendly" with tourists.
    Footage includes: Aung San Suu Kyi's release from house arrest, archival footage of Nelson Mandela, previous speeches/campaigns of Aung San Suu Kyi, and footage shot by Hillary Brown during her trip to Burma.
  - Various Reports on Burma, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:40:00] (Box 287, Video-cassette BU046)
    Edited report by Heather Kelly for Bay Area Video Coalition
    In refugee camp in ThaiBorder, 6000 people in the camp faced frequent cross border attacks by Burmese Army. Miriam, the women leader, said Karen National Union (KNU) gave up permanent bases and conducted guerilla warfare.
    In Myitkyina, northern Burma, jade mine workers mostly contracted AIDS virus. Drug abuse was rampant due to the cheap supplies and lack of occupational recreation. 67% of drug users were now believed to have contracted AIDS. Dr. Jacob: "Many came with AIDS symptoms and many more are coming. It has become the newest AIDS hotspot on earth."
    Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) invited Junta, ignoring the plea of nations of the earth. U.S. said it is ASEAN's responsibility to lead the junta to the right way. State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) accused U.S. of supporting terrorists. Aung San Suu Kyi: "Allowing Junta to join ASEAN is no credit to ASEAN."
    Students demonstrated in Bangkok.
    PTT Petroleum Authority of Thailand planned to build the final 10% of Yadana pipeline, even facing resistance from environmental andrights groups.
    U.S. sanction on Burma: Barnaard Pe Win: "The U.S. made a mistake to impose sanctions. Government did not suffer. Only the small entrepreneurs suffered. "SLORC: "We have nations who would trade with us. So why do we care? If Cuba can survive we will."
  - Images Asia: No Childhood At All (1997), NTSC VHS [TRT 00:25:00] (2 copies) (Box 287, Video-cassette BU047)
    Report on children and how they have suffered physically, mentally and emotionally under Burma's military regime. They are denied basic services and education, and are forced to work for the military regime and/or join the army.
    Footage of children breaking rocks, building tourist sites, carrying huge bags from boats to land, working at construction sites, irrigation schemes, road building, and mixing toxic chemicals. Footage of children training at various military camps, including the Tiger Camp under drug war lord Kun Sa. Testimonies of former child soldiers. Also includes footage of student demonstrations: December 6, 1996, at Hledan Intersection, Rangoon.
    Segment on how students risk their lives to demonstrate against the State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC). The SLORC responds with military retaliation. Footage of student demonstrations: "I believe that, starting from this day, this night, this place, at this time all of us must fight in unity for the dignity of past student leaders, in memory of those who fought in the colonial revolution, for future generations, for the people of Burma, and for our lives."
    From a United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF) report: "Many children in Burma are orphaned, abandoned, trafficked, exploited in the labor force, institutionalized or jailed. Across the country many children enjoy no childhood at all. They are simply put to work."
    Aung San Suu Kyi: "Children have become involved in forced labor lately, because their parents can't afford to take time off from whatever they are doing to make a living, so if you don't provide one person per family for forced labor then you are fined parents send their children to take their place."
    According to this report, classrooms are crowded, there is a shortage of textbooks, the dropout rate is high, and 40% of the children have never been to school. Ethnic children are worse off, dislocated by civil war, abandoned, or lost. Girls are likely to end up in the brothels and sweat shops across Thailand. Boys are forced to join the army.
    From a UNICEF report: "Children have become victims or participants in Burma's armed conflicts, used as porters, human shields or human minesweepers.Children are killed, forcibly conscripted, unwillingly separated from their families, kidnapped and tortured."
    The report states that conscription of children to the army is common, the army rounds up children at movie halls, tea shops, and even schools. Stories are told by runaway child soldiers:
    Shwe Hla, 7th grader: "After school the SLORC soldiers came and surrounded the school and arrested us if rich people paid a bribe, they would be freed of course, but we had no money."
    Naing Oo, age 16: "The commanders mixed large tablets with army rum and the soldiers would become aggressive."
    The SLORC says Burma is experiencing an economic boom, and shows off foreign imports.This report claims that only a small echelon of the society is prospering.
  - Nomad Production: Burma (1997), NTSC VHS [TRT 00:45:00] (2 copies) (Box 287, Video-cassette BU048)
    Produced by: Nomad Production
    Scenes of Shewdagon Pagoda Rangoon. Practice rituals of the Buddhists and this amazing landmark.
    Scenes of speedboats riding in Inlay Lake in Shan state, villages, trains of Mandalay Express, cars full of monks, river and Mingun.
    Skinny malnourished children are running traditional souvenir shop, selling famous Mingun Bell. There are jewelry shops, nuns of all ages.
    The grand ancient Mingun Temple was built by King Bodawpaya, over looking the Irrawaddy Pagoda.
    Scenes of sculptors carving statutes of Buddha, Shwesine factory, Mandalay moat, Foothill pagodas, Pagwet facial decoration, Kunya beatlenut and leaf, and River ferry.
    Aung San Suu Kyi's home, the National League for Democracy (NLD) Headquarters, and a news conference.
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): The 48th Independence Day Celebration, January 1996, NTSC VHS [TRT 02:00:00] (2 copies) (Box 287, Video-cassette BU049)
    Produced by: National League for Democracy Information
    Shift pavilions were decorated with flags, pictures and slogans. Enthusiastic crowds were brave despite the harassment by State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC).People were in lines. U Tin Oo entered as people applauded, then came, "Good health and good life!"
    U Ba Ba Sagaing Div, Master of Ceremonies. People freed pigeons to symbolize freedom, saluted the fallen martyrs and heroes of the struggle for democracy.